# Benjamin Rosenbaum

#### Widdendream Systems LLC

Gartenstr. 35, 4102 Binningen

076-483-0152

benjamin.rosenbaum.dc@gmail.com

26 years of experience in software development and IT, including Lean and Agile process coaching, architecture, design, development, implementation, analysis, requirements specification, and client support, in web development, web services, mobile. SOA, and client/server environments. Worked on projects for hospitals, healthcare finance agencies, banks, entertainment, human resources, and federal, state, cantonal, and municipal government.

#### **Skills**

Methodologies TDD, Lean, Agile, Kanban, Scrum, Human Centered Design,

Scaled Agile, Lean Canvas, XP, CI/CD, UML, OOA/OOD,

**BPMN** 

Languages Java, C#, Ruby, Python, JavaScript, Scala, SQL, HTML5/CSS3,

JSON, Elm, Haskell, XML, XSLT, C++, C, PHP, Perl, Lisp, Unix

shells

**Databases** MS SQL Server, MongoDB, Oracle, Postgres, Sybase, MySql

**Tools** AWS, Rails, Sinatra, jQuery, WPF, WCF, Ling, ASP.NET, MS

Entity Framework, ADO.NET, lodash, Kendo, Gatling, git, Github, Stash, Kanbanize, JIRA, TeamCity, sbt, maven, Subversion, VisualStudio.NET, SharePoint, Google and Facebook APIs, OData, Tomcat/Apache, JRun, IIS, Websphere, JUnit, NUnit, Eclipse, Ajax, Hibernate,

mockobjects, httpunit, log4j, NLog, TCP/IP, ODBC, COM

**Operating Systems** Linux, iOS, Android, Mac OS X, Windows, Solaris, FreeBSD

## **Education**

## Brown University, Providence, RI, USA

B.A., Computer Science, 1991 B.A., Religious Studies, 1991

#### **Certifications**

- Scaled Agile Framework Enterprise (SAFe) Program Consultant, October 2015
- Programming in HTML5 with JavaScript and CSS3, Microsoft, February 2014
- Certified Java 1.4 Programmer, Sun Microsystems

## **Experience**

Client

#### Widdendream Systems LLC

03/2016 to present Washington, DC; Basel, Switzerland

**Senior Software Architect** 

DC Health Benefit Exchange

**Environment** Ruby, Rails, Sinatra, AWS, MongoDB, Java, iOS, Android

- Led a distributed team in developing native iOS and Android mobile apps for healthcare brokers and individual enrollees.
- Gathered requirements, did agile process management, acted as product owner, wrote Ruby and Java code.
- Supported three project teams in adoption of Lean/Agile processes including Kanban boards and CI/CD.
- Coordinated APIs, processes, and SOA between various teams within the Health Benefits Exchange.

#### **Courage LLC Senior Innovation Program Manager**

09/2015 to 03/2016 Washington, DC, USA

Clients Office of the Chief Technology Officer, DC Government
Environment Lean/Agile coaching, Kanbanize, Python, JavaScript, lodash

- Helped establish DC's Technology Innovation program, providing strategic consulting to align OCTO's project portfolio with mayoral priorities.
- Applied Kanban, Scaled Agile, Lean Canvas, and Human Centered Design techniques to projects including prototype citizen involvement and criminal justice oversight websites.
- Contributed to citywide Open Source and Open Data initiatives.

#### Learning Objects Software Engineer V

06/2014 to 09/2015 Washington, DC, USA

**Clients** Elsevier, Sage Education, Café Learn, Lumen Learning **Environment** Java, Scala, PostgreSQL, Tomcat, REST, Angular, Gatling

- Developed personalized learning software including adaptive assessments and competency-based learning.
- Worked closely with customers, including top medical publishing house Elsevier.
- Provided technical leadership, mentoring other developers, and establishing standards.
- Drove company-wide adoption of software best practies such as increased automated unit and integration testing with data conditioning.

itsystems AG07/07 to 06/14Member of Technical StaffBasel, Switzerland

**Clients** Merien-Iselin Hospital, Roche, Eucomed, Paul Scherrer Institut,

City of Zurich, City of St. Gallen, Manor, Migros, Safruits

**Environment** .NET, C#, MS SQL Server, Web Services, HTML5, Javascript,

JQuery, WPF, XSLT, SharePoint, MatchPoint

• Technical lead for ProcessPoint, a Business Process Documentation system (BPMN/Flowchart).

• Spearheaded agile development techniques, introduced Kanban.

• Consulting, design, architecture, and implementation on a variety of custom software solutions (document management, collaboration platforms, web applications, data aggregation) for large, medium and small clients in medical, pharmaceutical, government, and retail sectors.

Avenity
Technical Architect
Reston, VA, USA

Environment
.NET, C#, MS SOL Server; Java, Oracle; Web Services, DHTML

• Designed and led development of a web-service based .NET reimplementation of a client's flagship public agency risk management solution, incorporating agile

• Helped design and implement Java-based custom web storefront, data analysis, and data management solution for one of the world's largest HR companies.

## **Computer Intelligence Associates**

development practices and TDD.

09/05 to 12/06 Washington, DC, USA

Client District of Columbia Office of the Chief Technology Officer
Environment NET, C#, MS SQL Server, Web Services, DHTML, CSS, SOA

- Designed and led development of a greenfield transportation permit issuing application, integrating with legacy systems, creating significant cost and time savings for utilities, business users, and government employees.
- Spearheaded adoption of Agile, TDD, incremental releases.

# **Compuware Corporation**

Architect

09/03 to 08/05 McLean, VA, USA

Professional Services Division Staff
Client National Science Foundation

**Environment** Java, Struts, Sybase, JRun, Solaris, JavaScript, Perl, C/C++, XSLT

- Analyst, architect, team lead, Java/J2EE expert on web-based funding, grant and document managment system with over 300,000 external users.
- Championed TDD, modern development tools, automated builds, and best practices.

# **COMIT Financial Systems AG**

**Senior Consultant** 

07/99 to 09/03 Basel, Switzerland

**Environment** 

**Environment** 

Java, PL/SQL, C++, JavaScript, Perl, XSLT, Tomcat/Apache, WebSphere, CORBA, Oracle, Solaris, Windows

- Helped design and develop of loan processing, account management, real estate valuation and credit rating applications for major Swiss banks.
- Championed code reuse, TDD, Design Patterns, CI/CD, open source, XML, UML, coding standards.
- Mentored 20-30 Java programmers across 3-5 projects.

## **Digital Addiction**

11/97 to 02/99 Laurel, MD, USA

Software Architect, Project Technical Lead

Visual C++, MFC, Windows 95/NT; C, Perl, PHP, MySQL, Apache, IRC, Linux, FreeBSD, Solaris

- Leading a small team, designed and developed a head-to-head, turn-based internet strategy game, 'Sanctum', based on collectible digital objects.
- Developed components for user interface, game logic, client/server communication with TCP/IP sockets, account management, database access, matchmaking, load balancing, collectible digital object trading, and e-commerce.
- Sanctum was awarded '1998 Online Game of the Year' by Game Industry News.

#### CareerBuilder Software Engineer

11/96 to 04/97 Reston, VA, USA

**Environment** 

Visual C++, MFC, MS SQL Server, Windows 95/NT

• Developed user interface, client/server connectivity, internet connectivity, and text search components for a Human Resources Management product, "Team Builder 2.0 ("Top Product of 1997", Human Rescource Executive magazine).

# Brilliant Nite Software Project Architect

05/94 to 10/96 McLean, VA, USA; Bern, Switzerland

**Environment** 

Delphi, Visual Basic, Borland C++/OWL, Windows 3.1 and 95

 Researched, designed, and prototyped an international multilingual smallbusiness accounting system.

## **Books that Work Software Engineer**

12/92 to 05/94 Palo Alto, CA, USA

**Environment** 

Borland and MPW C++, Windows 3.1 and Macintosh

• Developed 3D graphics libraries, user interface, and knowledgeable CAD objects for award-winning do-it-yourself products combining multimedia and user-friendly 3D design.

# **Ancillary Skills**

- · Native English speaker, fluent in German, proficient in Italian
- Have published nonfiction, fiction, and poetry in major websites (e.g. Motley Fool, Tor.com), national print magazines (e.g. Harper's, F&SF, Nature), best-of-the-year anthologies, and a college textbook; stories translated into over twenty languages; finalist for the Nebula, Hugo, World Fantasy, BSFA, and Sturgeon fiction writing awards.
- Board member (and President for two years) of a local synagogue, 2008-present.

#### References

Available on request